[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer org
slash software rethink DB is an open
source database for the real-time web
Slava Ock machette is the CEO of rethink
DB Slava what is rethink DB or rethink
UB is an open source distributed
database designed from the ground up for
the real-time web and real-time
applications and the idea is that you
know when we started the company we
noticed that the world is really moving
towards real-time people build much more
collaborative experiences for example
applications like slack or Google Docs
where people collaborate online and you
know when someone makes a change to
anything it's really important for for
other participants to see it right away
and we noticed that the database
architecture really wasn't written for
this so people make you know developers
they make all kinds of all kinds of
really complicated decisions to build
these apps and we thought hey this could
be dramatically easier you know let's
build a product that makes building
these kinds of apps much much easier to
do because that's where the world is
going and that's how we started rethink
and that's that's what it's for at a
slightly lower level what problems does
rethink DB solve at a lower level on
there the problem is so imagine you know
let's talk about the example of Google
Docs you have a document that the one
user is modifying and you have another
document that someone else is looking at
so what you have to do is whenever a
modification in document you know and
browser 8 happens you have to store it
somewhere and then push it back the
browser B so there's been tremendous
innovation on the front end with things
like you know web sockets and socket IO
and all kinds of client libraries to
make that possible
but on the back end it's still really
hard because when you're working with a
database you typically you know you just
on the way you query data is you send
the query you'll get a response
if you
want if you want new data you have to
send another query and get another
response so on a very simple level like
if you just write if you were to write
this application and in a naive way what
you do is you start querying the
database over and over again and the
loop let's say every few milliseconds
and of course that turns out to be a
really bad user experience because the
latency is too high you know you can
send a query every few milliseconds it
should people typically set it to
seconds and the second problem was if
you have a lot of concurrent users and
you start querying the database in a
loop you just bring down the database
right so it's really hard to do this
naively and then you can you know we can
talk a little bit about how people build
these applications today but on a lower
level which we think it'd be does this
the developer can say instead of just
sending a query if they can say okay I'm
subscribing to this information for
example I'm subscribing to all anything
that happens in this document and when
someone writes to the database the
database sends notifications though the
subscriber saying hey this particular
piece of data you were interested in
it's different now it's changed and this
is done by a push message so if you're
building your your collaborative
application you know each client can
just say okay I'm interested in this in
this specific piece of data or these
multiple specific pieces of data and
then anytime any client does anything
any modification you know we push a
message and and you can get it and
anybody who's interested in it can get
it so what that does is it makes it
dramatically so first of all it solves
the problem of barking down the database
arm so it's very scalable because the
database knows at all times what happens
I mean it can efficiently push these
messages and it solves the problem of
your infrastructure getting much more
complicated because it can do it in a
naive way typically so the way people do
it now is you know it's pretty hard you
have to add a lot of different pieces
and we take all of the complexity out so
the code becomes much simpler the
infrastructure becomes much simpler you
don't have to add a lot of a lot of
different moving pieces and the way we
do that is by pushing these messages
about data updates does that make sense
yes the push notification
and we will get into that but what
differentiates rethink from other
databases on the market what are the
most specific points of differentiation
so the biggest piece of differentiation
is we think UB is completely designed
around push architecture so you know
anything that happens in the database we
can push a message up to the user and
and I brought up a specific example of
you know the user is interested in this
piece of data but it's not just data
it's done for computations too so for
example you could say you know I'm
interested in the top 10 selling
products in my store and then anytime
something happens the database will
recompute this so it isn't just looking
at a specific document in the database
it's looking at a computation and at the
core everything to be there is a
computation engine that's designed for
push notifications and you know whenever
something changes we recompute things
efficiently push the message and what
that does is it makes building real-time
that real-time apps dramatically easier
it's the main piece of differentiation
and we're going to be and you know
there's a lot of other things like we
cared a lot about both the developers
and operations people so so the query
language is extremely convenient that's
very nice everything to be is much much
easier to scale than a lot of competing
systems it's really designed with ABS
people in mind the guarantees that we
offer are typically much more they're
much more significant than what you'd
get with a lot of database systems so
there's actually a lot in the internals
that differentiates and we think you be
able to come to small technical details
but on a high level the push
architecture is extremely important I
think it's one of the first databases in
the world to do this we will get into
the engineering that underlies that push
architecture but first how did rethink
dbo originated what is the origin story
the origin stories of my background I
grew up in New York City and I was you
know I'm a software engineer I was
working on Wall Street in the financial
industry and I was responsible actually
for building custom databases for some
of the high frequency trading use cases
we had and nothing of
she'll you know would do so so I've
worked there for a while I learned a lot
but I didn't really like the environment
I went to grad school and in grad school
I was studying brain simulation on
supercomputers so I learned a lot about
clustering I learned a lot about
distributed systems and then the
meantime I met my co-founder Michael who
was you know he was mainly doing a lot
of web development by the web
applications computer human-computer
interaction stuff like that and we met
we started talking and I told them you
know I told them about what I was doing
and he said hey you know this is a huge
problem on the web and you seem to know
a lot about it and we just started
brainstorming ideas we noticed that the
way people build and deploy web
applications is changing and these
changes are going to percolate through
the whole development stack so we
decided to start a company and this so
this was back on the East Coast in New
York and we kind of packed our bags and
move to California and incorporate it
and you know just never look back Refik
GB supports a push model as you
mentioned rather than the request
handling model could you give a broader
explanation of how that compares to
application development of the past
that's bet based on request response yes
so I talked a little bit about how if
you use request response you have to you
know you have to continuously query the
database which is really hard because
you end up bringing it down it's hard to
scale and the latency turns out to be
pretty bad and if you think about it if
you squint your eyes for a bit the
reason why request response model used
to work for databases on the web for so
long is because HTTP was request
response right so you send a request you
know the browser sends an HTTP request
to the web server the web server sends a
request so the database gets the
response sends the response but now that
we have WebSockets and the web server
often has to push data to the browser
the the top of the stack is no longer
request response it's much more
complicated right and what people try to
do it they try to shoehorn this request
response database model on top of a much
completely different model for building
web applications so that's why push push
is very
and I mentioned in naive way of doing it
where you just query the database over
and over again and you know that clearly
people learn very quickly that doesn't
work so then what they started doing
later is they start they figure out okay
this doesn't work we have to optimize it
and there's a couple of ways of doing it
you know but generally when you start
doing that your code becomes much more
complicated because you have to split
you have to split your code you have to
write to the database and then push a
message somewhere else and then you have
to have a piece of infrastructure for
keeping track of all these messages you
have to have code to route these
messages among you know among your
clients and if you have multiple web
servers if you're scaling your web
servers then the web servers have to
talk to each other they have to filter
out the messages so you don't saturate
your network you have to do all these
things and it's really really hard and
you know the experts in the space can
definitely do it it's clearly doable but
it's really hard and we think makes it
really really easy because you just use
your database directly and it's designed
to handle all of that complexity so so
the software engineer kind of pushes at
them you know pushes the burden
interesting you be and they don't have
to worry about that stuff does that make
sense yeah absolutely
so many applications build push in the
application layer on top of a database
why is it better to have that layer
within the database itself there are a
couple of reasons
arm so the first reason is the database
the database itself has a lot of
knowledge that the application doesn't
have so one canonical example of this is
suppose suppose you're trying to get you
know top 10 players in your game in real
time you can build and you want to push
that leaderboard to the clients in real
time show it to people in real time
so there you can't do this in the
application but it's really really hard
because if you for example learn that
your number 10 player drops out it's
very hard for you to know what the next
the next player is because the
application just doesn't have that data
so it would have to send a query to the
database and get it and it would have to
know which user to get so it's quite
challenging to do in the application
it's actually doable I mean people have
definitely
before but you have to deal with a lot
of custom code so for each interaction
you want to implement you have to write
a lot of custom code to deal with it you
have to deal with routing and you have
to add a message bus you know if you
ever want to scale and you have the
right routing code about that message
bus so you have to do all these things
and a lot of it becomes custom work and
you know in software engineering we talk
a lot about abstractions and we talk
about the fact that if the abstractions
are right then everything is easy and
everything kind of flows and if the
obstructions are wrong then everything
becomes really really complicated and
doing data manipulation in the
application like that it's kind of the
wrong abstraction because the
application just doesn't have that
information it's all custom code and you
could do this much much more elegantly
in the database
that's both more efficient and results
in a dramatically simpler application
code what is the full stack architecture
when the database is pushing rather than
pulling okay so people do this in
different ways I'm usually reading GB
users they tend to use nodejs sometimes
they use Ruby or Python
sometimes other languages like C sharp
or the JVM stack but generally and you
know sometimes it's not always the
browser sometimes it's the mobile phone
so it's kind of hard to generalize but
I'll try so generally what happens is
you have your web browser you have your
web client and it's communicating with
the web server why are some kind of a
socket protocol so web sockets typically
people you suck at i/o you could use
different libraries so on the front end
it's usually a framework like react or
angular then there's a WebSocket
connection to the web server and the web
server is usually no js' or python a
ruby and then that communicates with the
database wired everything to be drivers
so that would be the stack the real-time
stack if you use everything to be and if
you didn't use everything to be you'd
need the stack would be much more
complicated because you'd need a
database you'd need a message bus you'd
need a lot of custom code in the
application to push messages on the
message
barson to read from the message bus and
people often add a lot of other custom
code to hook into the database to kind
of get updates and do computations
you've mentioned messaging a couple
times now push is usually handled in a
messaging layer that is responsible for
durability and delivery guarantees and
other features is rethink really a
database with a messaging layer bundled
in okay so I think thinking about it as
a database with a message messaging
layer bundled in it's kind of a good
first approximation if you think about
it that way you'll probably be write
quite a bit about what we think that we
can do for people but it's not really
designed with a message box in mind so
message bosses are very different they
have different purposes you know as you
mentioned Jeff they guarantee delivery
they have a lot of different features
they're fobs are features we think does
this a little bit differently what we do
is instead of thinking about everything
is messages we think about it as changes
in the data so for example if you're
building a web application and you want
to show you want to re-render your Dom
every five milliseconds and show new
data every five milliseconds because if
you do it faster than that the user
doesn't care right it doesn't matter
they can see changes faster than that so
what we think a B will do it has a
feature called squash which will squash
updates so if multiple things if
multiple relevant changes happen within
a five millisecond period then we think
to be instead of sending multiple
messages to the clients that saying hey
stuff keeps changing it will wait five
milliseconds and then send a single
message saying here's the changes to the
data and if the changes intercept and it
will figure all that out and it will
send you the latest you know the latest
relevant piece of information so for web
developers you actually want that and of
course all of that is configurable and
people can turn it off and change that
but it's much more it's much better to
think of it as differences and data that
we inform people about instead of
messages because the use cases are
different and there are some things we
think we can't do right now you know
like the traditional message process
will do so if you need guaranteed
delivery and you need to make sure every
message that you push on a boss you see
like we think if he is not the best
product for that there's much much
better solutions what we do is we just
make sure you get the latest piece of
data you're interested in it's so it's
not about messages it's about
differences and data does that make
sense yeah yes
does rethink support pub/sub is there
like a pub/sub api somewhere so a couple
of people have built a pub subsystem on
top everything can be change sheets and
it's actually pretty easy there is some
code if you go through thing to be the
counselors dots I think we have an
example of how to build a pub sub system
so it's very easy to build on top of
feeds but we don't you know we don't
ship that natively it's not part of the
product real-time is a buzzword that
gets used a lot
how does rethink define a real-time
application we define a real-time
application as basically an application
when multiple users generally
collaborate and they need to see the
changes made by one user all day you
know the other users need to see it
within a very short period of time
probably under you know under whatever
whatever is possible in HTTP you would
say under 20 milliseconds although there
are some applications where the
requirement is there stricter and you
have to get the you know 5 milliseconds
or so when you have those more strict
requirements does the usage of rethink
change or does does rethink tend to just
provide that latency and and the
bottleneck is more on the application
developer know the user doesn't change
is pretty much the same so for our
change feeds or the users can say which
timeline they expect and you'd be
surprised sometimes you want it to be a
little bit higher like if you're
rendering Dom and there's a lot of stuff
going on like let's say you're updating
market data you know about stocks and
you have this pipe and it's changing
very quickly
you don't want to re-render the Dom more
than let's say every 20 milliseconds
because if you do that the experience
and the browser becomes bad so all the
user has to say is I care about updates
with
bond of time and then will bundle them
will dilute them will do all the work
and and send the information to the user
and the uses it's exactly the same
you've mentioned the word change feed a
couple times what is the definition of a
change feed a change feed is a query
everything to be just like any other
query except you tell rethink like hey
when you send me the response don't stop
keep sending me updates when something
changes so it's basically one way to
think about it as a cursor it's like a
cursor that never terminates so you open
this cursor and then whenever there's
updates that the results that the user
gets these updates what is the data
model of rethink DB we think it B is a
document store more specifically it's a
JSON store so what you store in the
database is usually JSON documents and
it's extended a little bit so you could
store you know geospatial data geo jason
binary data we extend Jason to deal this
time a little bit better and of course
it's all backwards compatible so you
could get JSON up so it's definitely a
document model and then you could build
relationships on top of that and do
joins which is a huge deal we think is
one of the only I think no sequel
products that supports distributed join
joint queries so it's it's a document
model but you could also model
relationships very effectively what
about the transaction model if I update
the database and as a result some pushes
occur to my application at what point is
the transaction considered complete so
the push model in rethink eBay is a
synchronous with respect to the rights
so when you do it right there's a lot of
guarantees that have to happen in a
distributed database you know to make
sure all the nodes all the relevant
notes got the right and so on then the
client gets the acknowledgement whenever
the data safely committed to disk the
push notification happens happens
asynchronously we send it to you know to
all the relevant clients that are
interested in it and what the clients
can do is there's some provisions and
we're extending that up quite a bit
actually to correlate the write the
write that happened to the message that
happens
you can for example tell okay like you
know I've received this message that
means all of these that means I've
received the message is relevant to all
of the rights you know like this one and
before that so we do a lot of that but
there is no transaction with respect to
push and messages because this doesn't
really work well on the web what about
the consistency model I'm sorry thank
you B is immediately consistent when you
do it right you get get a response
notification you read it you you
generally you always get you know you
can always see the write that you made
and with respect to a single document
you get all of the consistency and
durability guarantees that you would
expect of a relational database we're
very very serious about that stuff so
you know we're very serious about
people's data and you get you pretty
much get all the guarantees that you get
in a relational database but only as
long as you're looking at a single
document not across documents is
rethinkdb distributed or monolithic you
mean with respect to like the network in
terms of how people tend to implement it
if you have how people tend to use it oh
it's definitely distributed so people
typically start with a single you know
the download you think you'd be
typically on their laptop so you develop
you can develop in one note and then
when you need to scale people generally
build out clusters and they move up to
three knows then five and then they keep
going up so it's definitely distributed
so once they distribute what kind of
camp trade-offs does rethink DB make
okay so everything QB is hugely biased
or it's consistency if you have so if
you have a cluster or multi even
multiple data centers with a lot of
machines and then you have a split brain
scenario you can only write on one side
of the split brain that's guaranteed you
can read consistent data on on one side
of the split brain on the other side you
could read outdated data but not by
default so you have to pass a flag
saying I'm okay without data data so
whenever there is a partitioning
scenario we very quietly we're very
highly biased there is consistency than
availability and there
we do that is because it makes building
applications much simpler because you
don't duplication developer doesn't have
to deal with conflicts it just results
in a dramatically better developer
experience environment so we tell people
who need availability in the face of
partitioning network partitioning we
told them to use other products and
there's really good products for that
they're typically much harder to program
against but they solve that problem much
better what are the invariants that
rethink DB provides ok so this is a
little hard because we think is a big
product but I'd say the biggest
invariant is is if you write the data
and you get the acknowledgement you can
be sure that the data is in disk and
you're going to be able to get it later
if you make multiple changes to a
document those changes are atomic so you
know they're in a single document
they're either both gonna get written or
neither of them are gonna get written
you know if the power goes out it's not
going to corrupt your system so it's
it's all over to the traditional kind of
acid guarantees that you get in a
regular database these are invariants
and we think you be accepting everything
to be it's only true with respect to a
single document whereas in the
relational database you could do it
across multiple rows I'm gonna get
transactions across rows which is
impossible and everything is there a
scenario where we think DB can see stale
data yes so this is actually extremely
rare but there are situations where if
you have a multi node cluster and you
have what we call cascading split-brain
scenarios it's not just one failure in
the network it's multiple kind of
cascading failures and you know some of
the nodes fail while some other stuff
happens there is a possibility of stale
data so this is very rare and multiple
things have to go wrong but it's
possible and we actually have molds and
we think could deal with that stuff so
the user can specify okay I'm okay with
seeing stale data but get high
performance reads in these rare
situations or I don't want to see stale
data I always want consistent consistent
views but the reads are a little bit
slower so we let the user control
the behavior and kind of trade-off
performance and consistency could you
talk more about how rethink DB handles
write durability yeah so I mentioned a
couple of times that you know we care
very deeply about people's data because
it's obviously at the core of everything
and you get the same the same guarantees
for right durability that you get in a
you know in a traditional relational
database but on a lower level what
happens when the user does a right is so
let's say it's a distributed scenario
and you have you know three replicas
which means you've asked the database to
maintain three copies of your data so
what happens when the client does a
right is rethink you people send that
right to three different nodes in the
cluster and it will wait for the
majority of the nodes to acknowledge the
right when the majority of the nodes
acknowledge the bride everything
everything to be sends acknowledgement
to the client so then if anything fails
we have majority you have majority of
the nodes contain new data and with
timestamp everything and stuff like that
so if an if one of the nodes fails and
then restarts it will contact contact
all the relevant nodes I'm asked for the
latest updates and figure all of that
stuff out so those are rights are
handled on the in the distributed layer
and then undescore agenda that you know
the deals with it pretty much in a
similar way as any other traditional
database would there's a couple
differences we don't know if we have
time to go into that does that make
sense Jeff absolutely do you agree with
I mean you've mentioned a couple times
that there are scenarios where you need
a different store then then rethink do
you agree with the premise of polyglot
persistence that applications generally
need a variety of databases with varying
sets of features and guarantees so I
don't know how I feel about it
ideologically but empirically we always
see that in our user steps that's
exactly what the mem sequel CTO said I
really don't know that I didn't listen
to that podcast but yeah I mean it shows
up it's not just rethink though it's
people use three four five different
systems to do what they need
then sometimes in really big
organizations what we see is they have a
single store for example HBase where
they stole are there all their data and
then for custom use cases they take
slices of data from HBase that are
relevant to that use case and put it in
a completely different product and in
the build organization I mean they can
have dozens and dozens of different
products and hundreds of instances
across teams so yeah I'd say I agree
with polyglot persistence you're saying
you agree with it empirically though so
what is I mean is there some bright
future where developers only need one
database product that does everything
for them oh man ideologically I think
it's very very hard because the use
cases are really diverging for people
people are doing a lot of very very
different things and it's just you know
this diversity hasn't been around here
in the 90s like in the 90s all of the
things that we did were the same and now
there's just much more stuff that
happens in a typical infrastructure so I
honestly you know I look at a lot of
products like I'm very proud of what
we've done was we think and we think
it's amazing it's an amazing product for
the use of cases that we build it for
built it for but I also look at a lot of
other things people are doing and I'm
you know they're very very impressive
and they're so for example elasticsearch
it's just phenomenal for what it does
and I don't see you know I don't see how
they could do what we do and I didn't
see how we could do what they do well in
a single product so I think the web and
storage is probably going to move closer
to the UNIX philosophy where it's not
quiet you know do one thing and do it
well but it's do a small set of things
that are relevant to each other and do
that well so in the polyglot reality
that we live in
how does rethink DB operate alongside
other databases what role should it play
in a polyglot architecture so anything
can be integrates with a lot of other
database systems really nicely and in
particular change feeds make that make
that really really easy and there's some
libraries that have been written
the community to integrate written to me
was pretty much any database in
existence we tell people to use we think
for this real-time use cases very often
the authoritative source of data I can
tell you a little bit about what happens
in the wild you know in real deployments
so people will very often use
elasticsearch for some of the full-text
search functionality they'll use
sometimes message bosses to integrate
with with other applications that use
relational systems relational systems
are typically there for financial
processing where transactions across
multiple documents are important so
that's generally how it tends to work
out interesting we think DB is written
entirely in C++ this might be kind of a
naive question but why did you choose
C++ we chose C++ because performance was
very important and there were a couple
of like if you look at the options I
think there were a couple of options we
could have picked and probably on the
top of the list was C and C++
so with Joe C++ instead of C because it
gave us greater flexibility to deal with
kind of bigger architectures and a lot
of the early people that started
everything to be new C++ you know really
well so it was a natural natural choice
right now there's there's more options
there is go I here Ross this is
developing pretty nicely and I really
like that language so go has still has
some garbage collection issues that are
you know probably good enough for most
most applications but not databases and
Russ doesn't have GC in the same way but
it you know a lot of that stuff is still
being developed so I think for a
low-level infrastructure software like
this where latency is really important
and performance really important I mean
though there's been a lot of development
but C++ is still to this day probably
the best language I probably will stay
that way for a while do you have much
insight into what the things that go or
rust need to overcome in order to be
resilient and flexible enough as
languages to have databases written in
them
yes I actually I love programming
language is some kind of a pl nerd and
if you look at everything to be real
language you'll see that it was designed
by a lot of people who hopefully
understand programming languages really
well so I think about that a lot I think
was go there is it's just fundamentally
there is a garbage collector and they
keep you know they keep doing updates
and it keeps getting better and better
but for data based garbage collectors
are really bad because that means there
are stalls and you can get a variance in
the latency you know for queries and
that's really really bad for a database
product so forego I don't think it will
ever be a good systems language for the
kinds of products like databases just
because the garbage collector is baked
in like the moment you get a garbage
collector even if it's really really
good and then when that takes you know
decades getting that to be a good
language for system projects like
database is really hard for us I think
rust is a lot more promising because
it's designed for more lower lower level
use cases it's just a new language you
know it's gonna take some time to
develop people have to learn it they
have to learn best practices and you
know it's easy to learn a language it's
much harder to learn all of the all of
the icebergs that they're gonna get in
production when you're architecting your
application so yeah I think rust is a
lot is a lot more promising it's just
new so since you're saying that you
don't need garbage collection or you
don't want garbage collection when
you're writing a database to application
developers who are listening to this who
who all of the work that they've done
has been in garbage collection based
languages they probably understand that
garbage collection is this hazard it can
slow you down it does have problems but
how does your look what is the paradigm
shift you need to make when you are
writing an application that does not
necessitate garbage collection like
rethink dB
okay so so the problem was the garbage
collection is wonderful of course and
the problem with garbage collection is
latency so if the GC kxn
it's gonna stall it's gonna stall your
thread hopefully only a single thread
and then when a query comes in that
stall is gonna be visible in the latency
that the user is gonna see so you can't
do that right that's that's very very
important
it's very important in the database to
have as little latency variance as
possible if you don't use garbage
collection for example if you use C++
then you're really switching to a whole
slew of other techniques and so some of
the the best you know the best thing you
can do is you can know really well the
the lifetime of all your objects and if
you can tell the lifetime of your
objects you can just do manual memory
management and you can you know the
allocate memory when it makes sense and
it works really well for example with
short queries because if I do a short
query I know when it begins and I know
when in the ends and I can just be
allocate all the objects at the end of
the query so that you know that's
extremely fast it's very efficient and
works really well you know and you don't
need garbage collection you don't have
to deal with latency issues if you have
longer queries of course things get more
complicated because you might need to
deallocate memory in the middle and
there's all kinds of ways of doing it
you could be a shared pointers you could
you know you scope pointers and shared
pointers are really cool except you can
have you know cycles so you have to
design your code in a certain way so
you're really you're going down a rabbit
hole if you're not using garbage
collection that's it's a whole other
thing
so speaking of rabbit holes we can go
down rethink DB is written in C++ but
drivers exist for Ruby and Python and
JavaScript and other languages could you
describe the functions of a database
driver and how a database driver
interacts with a C++ database
application yes so the function of
everything to be driver um it's it's
interesting because it was very
important for us to give people a query
language that doesn't feel like they
don't have to manipulate strings right
it should feel like an API like the
library so when you're querying written
giving in Python it feels like you're
just writing Python code if you're
querying it in Ruby it feels like you're
writing Ruby code and so on
what the driver does is it's really a
thin layer that integrates extremely
well into the development environment
that you're used to so it feels like
you're writing in the language you know
that you're writing you that's the
function of everything to be driver to
provide people with the best possible
user experience the query the database
now the way the driver communicates with
everything to be is we have a wire
protocol and it's public you know it's
unwritten give me the thumbs large Docs
anybody could write a write a driver
that interacts was this wire protocol
and and it'll work with the server the
wire protocol is it's you know it's for
TCP so it starts out as binary but it's
basically JSON so you could you know you
just send JSON on the wire the database
interprets it and and sends back a
response and it's very efficient it's
very fast it's in it's relatively easy
to implement so so that's why actually
there's been so many community develop
drivers
so we've dive down deep I'd like to zoom
out again how does a developer get
started with rethink DB well the easiest
way is to go to everything to be calm
and kind of read a little bit about on
what it does for you and if it makes
sense you can download it very easily
it's available in OS X right now buy a
brew or you know a package manager dmg
it's also available on pretty much all
flavors of Linux we're currently working
in a Windows port that's gonna be
available pretty soon but you could also
do it in docker or you can deploy it in
the cloud you could use um compose i/o
which is one our partners that will let
you deploy we think in the cloud and a
lot of people actually use them just to
get everything give you server for
development you know so there's many
many ways to to just install it it's
really simple it only takes a few
seconds and then we have really good
documentation and we have a lot of
tutorials and we think you be calm and a
lot of people in the community have
built a lot of tutorials so I'd get
started that way I'd go through our
guide it's it's it's quite simple and
then if you have a specific stack like
for example let's say you use angularjs
there's some specific tutorials for how
to get started with everything to be an
angular for example
you know some the same thing for other
frameworks is there a notable developer
experience difference between a user on
a rail stack versus an angular or a
spring stack a rail yeah so we'll see
we're kind of jumping a little bit
because angular is a pronoun framework
and rail sure okay we express J a stack
or a mean stack yeah so so generally the
user experience is really nice in
node.js because node.js is in a
synchronous language right so it works
much much better with change speeds if
you use Ruby or Python if you're just
using everything to be without change
trees it's pretty similar to using any
other database and it's really nice if
you start using change feeds in in Ruby
and Python and other languages like that
that don't have a synchronous behavior
built in you have to use some of the
libraries like twisted or event machine
so or you know I think IO and Python
there's a lot of options so yeah there's
a little bit of difference a little bit
of differences in each in each stack but
generally it's very very similar like
the driver is look almost exactly the
same so if you have a Python 510 you'll
be called and you look at it you can
convert it to Ruby very trivially so
meteor is a JavaScript application
framework for building real-time apps
that leverages nodejs
and it seems to me that meteor would
have a lot of synergies with rethink DB
but maybe I'm off-base here is that
accurate or do you know much about
meteor oh that's totally accurate so we
actually know the team and when we were
designing change feeds
the first thing we do is we met with the
meteor team and we said hey guys you
know what do you see in the wild what
are the important use cases for users so
we kind of collaborated with them to
design design defeats
anything to be when it comes to the API
in architectural II all that happened a
lot earlier but but the API and the user
facing stuff was done in conjunction
with the meteor team and some people
have done an integration with everything
to be in neither there's still a little
bit more work that needs to happen
before it's production-grade but people
can probably start building
on top of it now so yeah there's
definitely I think what meteor has done
is all of that complexity they've baked
it into the media framework and took it
away from from application developers
but because they're dealing with
database systems it's hard to scale for
example meteor doesn't work with like
Charlotte charted databases right now so
yeah it's very close we work pretty
closely with them and they've been
immensely helpful and providing
information about what needs to happen
you know I in the database layer to have
a phenomenal user experience for the
application developer is meteor a
leading indicator for how application
development is going to be done in the
future I think there is a lot of
innovation going on in application
development and people are trying so the
world has clearly changed like the kinds
of apps we're building is totally
different and people are trying a lot of
different ideas so if you look at
paradigms you know angular does it one
way
Facebook's react does it a different way
a meteor does it a third way I think
it's very hard to tell on which way it's
going to go but it's I think it's pretty
clear to everyone that it's it's gonna
change it's already changed what is r eq
l r eq l is everything to be query
language and it's a curling which we
design with a couple of important design
goals so one is we wanted people to have
a really really good experience
developing in their native language so
you know you're writing python r equal
code looks just like Python code for
example the second thing we wanted this
we wanted it to be very efficient so
when you write a repo query and you send
it send it to the cluster it's all
execute in the cluster the class or
figures out where to send it how you
know how to get the data how to dole
that stuff and you just get a response
so R equal is really really wonderful to
use and again if you got everything to
be the console our Doc's um you can
learn a lot about how it works why it
works and how easy it is to get started
what does it mean to have chainable
queries chainable queries is for for
listeners who've used jQuery before
you're already used to the
to this idea the year or actually for
listeners who views best we bash before
I'm on the command line you are hurrying
right just currying in programming yeah
so this decide you actually shows up in
a lot of different in a lot of different
cases but generally and we think so
imagine you know you have your table
that has a bunch of documents let's say
of a table users that stores the user
data then what you can do is you can
chain a command on top of that so let's
say you wanted to join it with an
organization they work list you say
table users dot join you know company
and then after that let's say you wanted
to pull out only the fields you wanted
to say say dot Plock you know user
company and then so you can keep doing
this you can keep adding commands and
then the data flows from left to right
so sort of like pipe and dash or like
dot in jQuery and you can basically
manipulate data in very very
sophisticated ways but the user it feels
extremely natural cuz you're just
building out this query from left to
right and anytime you get more data or
less data if you're narrow it you figure
out okay here's the next thing I'm gonna
do so it's an extremely intuitive way to
building very complicated data queries
that that you couldn't really do so
intuitively in something like sequel for
example to emphasize this could you
explain what happens when I write a
series of chained queries maybe you
could give an example and then you call
run on the query chain explain in a
little more detail what happens yeah so
let's say I say table users that join
you know company dot plot user name
company name dot run so what I've done
there is I took all the data from my
users table they've joined it with my
company table I only pulled out the user
name and company name and then it typed
that run and passes a connection which
means ok it's time to run you know the
run to run the query so what happens is
the driver will take this whole query
the whole thing so not just the first
piece than the second piece it will take
the whole thing packaged it up in a JSON
wire protocol and send it to the cluster
so the whole thing gets executed in the
database server nothing happens on the
client the database server will get the
query and the
would be in one node or if your sharted
or replicated which would be in multiple
nodes and it said the database will get
this query it will figure out where all
of the data is it will send the relevant
messages inside the cluster do the
computations get the data back and then
send it to the user so from a user's
point of view you don't have to care if
it's distributor or not you just you
know you just write your query
everything gets executed on the under
search on the server and the cluster and
it can actually get really complex like
you could do MapReduce you could do
aggregations you could do computations
you could do a ton of different stuff
and all of that is handled by database
server rethink DB is in production at
hundreds of startups and consulting
studios and fortune 500 companies could
you give an example about how a user
from one of these companies is taking
advantage of rethink DB yeah so one
example we give us jive software on so
Jeff software it's a public company
they've built a protocol jive chime and
it's basically it's a messaging product
for for their users it's similar to
slack or HipChat that people have used
up before it but it's designed for you
know jive jive dolce or jive sweet suite
of products so messaging is an example
that comes up a lot we have a lot of
really interesting users and a lot of
different verticals some of one of my
favorite ones is a company called seem
um that does gaming and taking on
multiplayer multiplayer gaming and and
they usually think to be quite a bit
we're actually working right now on
video case studies with a lot of our
customers that we'll be publishing
pretty soon and what we do is we go out
we interview some of the folks there and
we ask them hey what do you like about
the product what do you not like it you
know how did it work out for you what's
the use case so we'll be publishing
video series pretty soon and I'm very
excited about it because there's some
really cool use cases everything to be
that I can't wait to tell people about
can you give any previews on that like
what are the commonalities between what
people say they really like about
rethink so the common things people say
is they really like the push model
because it makes their life dramatically
easier when they build the application
they really like the flexibility of the
career language the fact that you could
do joins and how easy it is to write
and they really like the fact that when
you deploy everything to be and you need
to scale it the operational story is
actually really really good arms
operations people love the product
because they didn't they no longer have
to you know wake up in the middle of the
night to deal with problems so these are
generally three things people people say
I can't talk about specific stories and
I'd have to coordinate it with some
people here but yeah I'm very excited
and we're gonna publish a lot of that
stuff really soon
could you talk any more about how you
would make a messaging application using
rethink or like what are the things that
you don't have to do because you have
rethink or you could talk about games or
maybe the commonalities between those
two verticals yeah so messaging well in
any one game so in case of games if you
have a multiplayer game and let's say
you have a character in a specific
location and the game and lots of other
players around them and then the
character moves so let's say in a
strategy game you know everyone else to
find that out so you need to push that
notification to all the other players in
messaging whenever someone says
something you need to send a message to
everyone who's interested so for example
you know it's like there are channels
and if someone says something in the
channel anybody could subscribe to the
channel needs to see need to see the
message so that's kind of the
commonalities the fact that you're
pushing pushing data so if you were to
do this the naive way you'd have to
query the database all the time to get
the messages and we talked about how
that doesn't work so what people start
doing is they start editing they start
adding pieces of infrastructure like
pops up and then anytime someone sends a
message what they do is they they split
the codebase so the first part of the
code says okay write this to the
database because I might need this later
the second part of the code says push it
on a message bus and then there is a
separate piece of code that has to
maintain all of the channels and all of
that information he typically also
stored it in the database in them
whenever someone joins a channel leave
the channel you have to configure your
message bus to account for all that
stuff so that's the kind of code you'd
have to write and then in the UI and the
web servers it'd have to write a lot of
code
propagate that back you know to the user
which we think you don't need the
message bus you don't need to write any
of that routing code you just say so
when someone you don't have to split
your code so when someone you know sends
a message you just write it to the
database and on the receiving end you
say you know this logged in user cares
about these channels and then anytime
someone writes to those channels they
the part of the code that deals with
that user is just gonna get a message
saying hey here's messages and all the
channels this particular user cares
about so that becomes much much simpler
we talked about this some at the
beginning but I want to ask again after
we've delved into the technical details
what is the key breakthrough what are
the breakthroughs of rethink DB what is
being rethought so we started with kind
of throwing out all of the assumptions
about database systems and starting from
scratch and what we learned after a long
time of doing this is that and we kind
of suspected you know suspected a lot of
this would happen but so when you're
dealing with disk and you're dealing
with queries and you're dealing with all
of the traditional like database storage
stuff the systems that were designed you
know 20 or 30 years ago
are absolutely rock-solid and you want a
lot of that you don't want to rethink
and you have that stuff like when you're
storing data
you know we've solved those problems
those solutions are really really good
you don't want to be rethinking anything
it's just I mean those things are just
really well done and people have put a
lot of effort into that and a lot of
thought a lot of brainpower a lot of
money and those solutions are really
good when you're dealing with api's that
is the part where you need to rethink a
lot of things because because the way
people build applications right now you
know in 2015 it's just so different from
the way we were doing it even five or
ten years ago all of that stuff is
different the requirements are different
so we're thinking that is really
important and another thing that and
another piece of innovation that
happened for it recently is the idea of
distributed systems because you can't
fit data you know on a single machine
anymore you can't meet performance
varmints in the single machine anymore
so you have to rethink that part and you
have to you know build a distributed
system which is really really hard so
the part that we've done that I'm really
proud of this the distributed system and
we thing to be you know I think it's
it's excellent it's really well-designed
it's very safe it's very very easy to
use so I'm very happy for that are equal
I think it's very well designed very
easy to use very intuitive to write
queries and the idea of change feeds the
idea of building the whole architecture
around push I think I'm also really
proud of because it legitimately
like makes people's lives a hundred
times easier if they're building these
kinds of apps so these are the things
we've done differently and on the
storage side and just kind of
traditional database stuff like asset
guarantees and all that we try to stay
as close to all the work that people
have done you know in the past probably
half a century in the database world
because if we think that far doesn't
need to be rethought and it's really
really well done already what is the
business model behind rethink DB the
company and is is there a close analog
maybe Red Hat or cloud era and how does
this affect the developer okay so
everything QB his open source and we're
open source
you know both functionally because the
code is online but also in spirit
because all the development happens in
github so anybody could don't get
habituates and features as they're being
designed and we're collaborating really
closely with our developer community and
like the user community is absolutely
wonderful it's very vibrant I would get
a lot of feedback so the whole thing is
open source as far as business model we
provide a lot of services to
organizations we provide training both
on-site and online to help people bring
we bring their developers up with
everything to be and I'll bring them up
to speed we do developer support so as
people build applications we can help
them learn things and get to market
faster we do production support so if
something goes wrong you know we would
help people out generally we do support
or slack so they get a real-time channel
to record development team and we can
use other you know other message systems
too so people really love love the
support model so that
what we're doing right now we do health
checks for people you know when they
deploy in production things like that
and we also have a lot of plans for
different services on top everything to
be that will make people's lives a lot
easier and I can talk about that right
now but hopefully it's gonna start
coming out you know next year so there's
a lot of really exciting exciting stuff
we're working on but right now it's been
a lot of just basically doing services
for people and helping out with getting
with you know getting apps developed
getting into production and making sure
everything stays stays great when the
ones the app is out so you've mentioned
a couple resources that aren't quite
ready for publication yet where can
people where can I put what in the show
notes that if people click on these
pointers in you know a few months or
three months or five months these
resources will be available where should
I point people to if they want to find
out more about rethink DB I would point
people to everything to be calm that's
the biggest you know the biggest
repository of information unwilling to
be and it's it's pretty easy to read as
well design there's a lot of them for
their people should should be able to
get you know a lot of information we're
also on Twitter so everything to be on
Twitter we're very active their response
on the most questions so if users have a
question you can just bring us
everything to be on Twitter we will
respond my personal email address here
is Slavitt we think you be calm so feel
free to send me an email if you have any
questions and output you know it's it
gets sometimes quite hard but I'll try
very hard to respond to every email so
yeah I'd say use these resources it's
just I'm kind of also github github is
another good one so waiting to be on
github is very active and everyone's
very responsive are there any closing
thoughts on rethink DB or application
development or computer science that
you'd like to provide to my listeners
yeah well we're very excited about
what's going on in the web because
there's a lot of innovation there's a
lot of innovation happening in the
browser and this is really important
because it's really changing the way the
way people build web applications you
know there's been angular and media
react is doing some quite amazing things
and as people build more and more
sophisticated front-end applications it
becomes quite clear that the rest of the
stack needs to change too because things
get very complicated so that's why we
started we thing to be in and we're very
excited about a lot of the work that
we're doing so the first part I wanted
to say the second part is that I wanted
to thank all of the open source
community people that have been engaged
with everything to be that have been so
helpful you know going to hackathons and
doing tutorials for people going to
meetups giving feature suggestions bug
reports you know helping with feature
design thank you guys so much the
product couldn't couldn't have been
nearly as good as it is now without your
help thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at SZ -
radioman to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on iTunes
mention a message us on Twitter at se
radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on Lincoln
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us a team at SES radio net this and all
other episodes of SU radio is licensed
under the creative commons 2.5 license
thanks again for your support
[Music]
[Applause]
you
[Music]